I don't know what the hell I'm doing here.
أنا لا أعرف ماذا الذي أفعله هنا بحق الجحيم.
I was born in a Scots Presbyterian ghetto in Canada,
لقد ولدت في غيتو الاسكتلندية في كندا
and dropped out of high school. I don't own a cell phone,
و تركت المدرسة الثانوية. أنا لا أملك هاتفا جوالا
and I paint on paper using gouache, which hasn't changed in 600 years.
وارسم على الورق باستخدام الغواش ، والتي لم يتغير منذ 600 عام
But about three years ago I had an art show in New York,
ولكن منذ حوالي ثلاث سنوات كان لي معرض للفن في نيويورك ،
and I titled it "Serious Nonsense."
اخترت له عنوان هو "هراء جاد".
So I think I'm actually the first one here -- I lead.
لذلك اعتقد انني في الواقع اول واحد هنا -- أنا الرائد.
I called it "Serious Nonsense" because on the serious side,
دعوته "هراء جاد"لأنه على الجانب الجاد،
I use a technique of painstaking realism of editorial illustration
أستخدم أسلوب الواقعية المضنية من التوضيح التحريري
from when I was a kid. I copied it and I never unlearned it --
منذ أن كنت طفلا. حفظت ذلك ، ولم أنسه أبدا -
it's the only style I know. And it's very kind of staid and formal.
انه النمط الوحيد الذي أعرفه. وهو نوع رزين وغير رسمي.
And meanwhile, I use nonsense, as you can see.
وفى نفس الوقت ، فأنا استخدم الهراء ، كما ترون.
This is a Scottish castle where people are playing golf indoors,
هذه هي قلعة اسكتلندية حيث يلعب الناس في منازلهم لعبة الغولف ،
and the trick was to bang the golf ball off of suits of armor --
وكانت الخدعة هى فرقعة كرة الغولف من على بدلات الدروع
which you can't see there.
و التي لن تتمكنوا من مشاهدتها هناك
This was one of a series called "Zany Afternoons," which became a book.
وكانت هذه واحدة من سلسلة تسمى "المهرج بعد الظهر" ، والتي أصبحت كتابا.
This is a home-built rocket-propelled car. That's a 1953 Henry J --
هذه هي سيارة محلية الصنع تعمل بالدفع الصاروخي. وهذا هو هنري جيه 1953
I'm a bug for authenticity -- in a quiet neighborhood in Toledo.
للعلم انا شائبة -- في حي هادئ في توليدو.
This is my submission for the L.A. Museum of Film.
هذا هو بلدي ما قدمته متحف لوس انجليس للسينما.
You can probably tell Frank Gehry and I come from the same town.
من المحتمل أن نقول أننى و فرانك جيري ننتمى لنفس المدينة.
My work is so personal and so strange
عملي شخصي جدا وغريب جدا
that I have to invent my own lexicon for it.
لدرجة أنه يتحتم على ابتكار قاموس له
And I work a lot in what I call "retrofuturism,"
وأعمل كثيرا في ما أسميه retrofuturism -المستقبلية الرجعية-
which is looking back to see how yesterday viewed tomorrow.
وهى أن ننظر إلى الوراء لنرى كيف رأى الاجداد الغد
And they're always wrong, always hilariously, optimistically wrong.
وهم على خطأ دائما ، دائما و بشكل مثير للضحك على خطأ ، مخطئون بتفاؤل
And the peak time for that was the 30s,
ووقت الذروة لهذا الأمر كان الثلاثينيات
because the Depression was so dismal
لأن الكساد الاقتصادي كان كئيبا جدا
that anything to get away from the present into the future ...
فما كان من شىء يستطيع أن يهرب من الحاضر الى الماضى
and technology was going to carry us along.
و التكنولوجيا كانت لتهيجنا
This is Popular Workbench. Popular science magazines in those days --
هذا هو بوبيولار وركبينش. مجلات علمية مبسطة في تلك الأيام --
I had a huge collection of them from the '30s --
كان لدي مجموعة ضخمة منها من الثلاثينيات
all they are is just poor people being asked to make sunglasses
كلها عن الفقراء الذين طلب منهم ان يصنعوا النظارات الشمسية
out of wire coat hangers and everything improvised
بـاستخدام شماعات الملابس المصنوعة من السلك ، وكل شيء مرتجل
and dreaming about these wonderful giant radio robots
وتحلم بهذه بأجهزة الراديو العملاقة الرائعة تلك
playing ice hockey at 300 miles an hour --
تلعب هوكي الجليد بسرعة 300 ميلا في الساعة
it's all going to happen, it's all going to be wonderful.
سيحدث كل هذا ، كل شيء سيكون رائعا.
Automotive retrofuturism is one of my specialties.
المستقبلية الرجعية فى مجال السيارات هو واحد من تخصصاتى .
I was both an automobile illustrator and an advertising automobile copywriter,
وكنت على حد سواء أرسم السيارات و أؤلف الإعلانات للسيارات
so I have a lot of revenge to take on the subject.
لذلك أنا لدي الكثير من الحق لتولي هذا الموضوع.
Detroit has always been halfway into the future -- the advertising half.
وقد كانت ديترويت دائما في منتصف الطريق الى المستقبل -- النصف الإعلانى --
This is the '58 Bulgemobile: so new, they make tomorrow look like yesterday.
هذا هو Bulgemobile '58 جديدة جدا ، حتى أنها تجعل الغد يبدو مثل الأمس
This is a chain gang of guys admiring the car.
هذه هي عصابة من الرجال أعجبت بالسيارة
That's from a whole catalog -- it's 18 pages or so --
وهذا من كتالوج كامل يقع فى 18 صفحة أو نحو ذلك
ran back in the days of the Lampoon, where I cut my teeth.
أعيد تشغيله في أيام لامبون حيث شذبت اسناني
Techno-archaeology is digging back and finding past miracles that never happened --
علم الآثارالتكنولوجي يعود مرة أخرى ، ويكشف عن معجزات سابقة لم تحدث أبدا --
for good reason, usually.
عادة ما يكون لسبب وجيه.
The zeppelin -- this was from a brochure about the zeppelin
والمنطاد-- كان هذا من كتيب حول المناطياد
based, obviously, on the Hindenburg.
يستند ، من الواضح ، على هندنبرج.
But the zeppelin was the biggest thing that ever moved made by man.
ولكن كان المنطاد أكبرشيء تحرك صنعه الإنسان
And it carried 56 people at the speed of a Buick at an altitude you could hear dogs bark,
وكان يحمل 56 شخصا في سرعة بويك على ارتفاع تسمع عنده الكلاب تنبح
and it cost twice as much as a first-class cabin on the Normandie to fly it.
ويكلف ضعفي مقصورة الدرجة الأولى على نورماندي للطيران على متنه.
So the Hindenburg wasn't, you know, it was inevitable it was going to go.
لذلك لم يكن هندنبرج ، تعلمون ، كان لا بد انه سيذهب.
This is auto-gyro jousting in Malibu in the 30s.
هذه مروحية الية تتنافس في ماليبو في الثلاثينيات
The auto-gyro couldn't wait for the invention of the helicopter,
لم تستطع الانتظار لاختراع الهليكوبتر،
but it should have -- it wasn't a big success.
ولكن كان يجب أن تنتظر -- لم يكن نجاحا كبيرا.
It's the only Spanish innovation, technologically, of the 20th century, by the way.
انها الابتكارالإسباني الوحيد، من الناحية التكنولوجية ، في القرن العشرين، بالمناسبة.
You needed to know that.
أنت بحاجة لمعرفة ذلك.
The flying car which never got off the ground -- it was a post-war dream.
السيارة الطائرة التي لا تقلع من الأرض أبدًا -- كانت حلما في فترة ما بعد الحرب.
My old man used to tell me we were going to get a flying car.
ورجل بلادي القديمة كان يقول لي نحن ذاهبون للحصول على سيارة تطير
This is pitched into the future from 1946,
هذا قذفني في المستقبل منذ عام 1946
looking at the day all American families have them.
أنظر اليوم, جميع العائلات الاميركية لديهم منها.
"There's Moscow, Shirley. Hope they speak Esperanto!"
"موسكو هناك، شيرلي. امل أن يكونوا يتكلمون لغة الاسبرانتو."
Faux-nostalgia, which I'm sort of -- not, say, famous for, but I work an awful lot in it.
الحنين المزيف ، والذي أنا نوعا ما أعانيه-- ولست، اقول، أنني أشتهر به ، ولكن أنا أعمل على جزء كبير فيه
It's the achingly sentimental yearning for times that never happened.
انه توق عاطفي مؤلم وموجع لأوقات لم تحدث أبدا.
Somebody once said that nostalgia is the one utterly most useless human emotion --
قال أحدهم ذات مرة أن الحنين هو تماما أكثر العواطف الإنسانية بلا فائدة
so I think that’s a case for serious play.
لذلك أعتقد أن هذه حالة للعب مهم
This is emblematic of it -- this is wing dining,
هذا هو رمز له-- هذا جناح الطعام
recalling those balmy summer days somewhere over France in the 20s,
إذ يشير إلى تلك الأيام الصيفية المعتدلة في فرنسا في العشرينيات
dining on the wing of a plane. You can't see it very well here,
يتناول الطعام على جناح الطائرة. لا يمكنك رؤيتها بشكل جيد للغاية هنا
but that's Hemingway reading some pages from his new novel
ولكن هذا همنغواي يقرأ بعض صفحات من روايته الجديدة
to Fitzgerald and Ford Madox Ford until the slipstream blows him away.
لفيتزجيرالد وفورد مادوكس فورد حتى أطاحت به تيارات المروحة
This is tank polo in the South Hamptons.
هذه هي لعبة البولو دبابات في جنوب هامبتون. هذا هو
The brainless rich are more fun to make fun of than anybody. I do a lot of that.
الأغنياء البلهاء أكثر متعة في السخرية من أي شخص اخر. أفعل هذا كثيرا.
And authenticity is a major part of my serious nonsense.
والأصالة هي جزء كبير من هرائي الخطير.
I think it adds a huge amount.
وأعتقد أنه يضيف كمية ضخمة.
Those, for example, are Mark IV British tanks from 1916.
هؤلاء ، على سبيل المثال ، دبابات مارك الرابع البريطانية من عام 1916
They had two machine guns and a cannon,
وكان لكل منها رشاشان ومدفع
and they had 90 horsepower Ricardo engines.
وكان لديهم محركات ريكاردو بقدرة 90 حصانا .
They went five miles an hour and inside it was 105 degrees in the pitch dark.
تسير بسرعة خمسة أميال في الساعة وبالداخل كانت درجة الحرارة 105 درجة في الظلام الدامس
And they had a canary hung inside the thing
وكان لديهم كناري معلق داخل الشيء
to make sure the Germans weren't going to use gas.
للتأكد من أن الألمان لم يكونوا ينوون استخدام الغاز.
Happy little story, isn't it?
قصة صغيرة سعيدة ، أليس كذلك؟
This is Motor Ritz Towers in Manhattan in the 30s,
هذة هي أبراج ريتز للمحركات في مانهاتن في الثلاثينيات
where you drove up to your front door, if you had the guts.
حيث دفع ما يصل الى الباب الأمامي الخاص بك ، إذا كان لديك الشجاعة
Anybody who was anybody had an apartment there.
وكان بوسع أي شخص عادي امتلاك شقة هناك
I managed to stick in both the zeppelin and an ocean liner out of sheer enthusiasm.
تمكنت من التمسك بكل من المنطاد وعابرة محيطات من الحماس الكبير
And I love cigars -- there's a cigar billboard down there.
وأنا أحب السيجار -- هناك لوحة السيجار هنا بالأسفل.
And faux-nostalgia works even in serious subjects like war.
والحنين مزيف يعمل حتى في مواضيع خطيرة مثل الحرب.
This is those wonderful days of the Battle of Britain in 1940,
هذه هي تلك الأيام الرائعة من معركة بريطانيا في عام 1940
when a Messerschmitt ME109 bursts into the House of Commons
عندما اقتحمت ME109 رشقات نارية في مجلس العموم
and buzzes around, just to piss off Churchill, who's down there somewhere.
ودوت حول المكان، لمجرد أن تغضب تشرشل ، الذي كان موجودا هناك في مكان ما.
It's a fond memory of times past.
انها ذكرى عزيزة من الاوقات الماضية.
Hyperbolic overkill is a way of taking exaggeration to the absolute ultimate limit,
المبالغة المغرقة هي وسيلة لأخذ المبالغة الى نهاية المطاف المطلقة ،
just for the fun of it. This was a piece I did -- a brochure again --
فقط للمتعة. كان هذا قطعة صممتها -كتيب ثانية-
"RMS Tyrannic: The Biggest Thing in All the World."
ار.ام.اس تايرانيك، اضخم شيء في كل العالم.
The copy, which you can't see because it goes on and on for several pages,
النسخة ، والتي لم تتمكن من مشاهدة لأنها تطول على عدة صفحات ،
says that steerage passengers can't get their to bunks before the voyage is over,
وتقول ان الركاب لا يمكنهم الحصول على سريرقبل انتهاء الرحلة
and it's so safe it carries no insurance.
وانها آمنة لذلك لا تحمل اي تأمين.
It's obviously modeled on the Titanic.
وعلى غرار من الواضح انه في تيتانك.
But it's not a cri de coeur about man's hubris in the face of the elements.
ولكنها ليست مرثية عن الإنسان في مواجهة العناصر --
It's just a sick, silly joke.
انها مجرد نكتة سخيفة مريضة.
Shamelessly cheap is something, I think -- this will wake you up.
هي رخيصة ولا خجل وهذا شيء ، أعتقد -- وهذا سوف يوقظكم.
It has no meaning, just -- Desoto discovers the Mississippi,
ليس لها معنى ، تماما -- ديسوتو يكتشف الميسيسيبي ،
and it's a Desoto discovering the Mississippi.
وهذا ديسوتو يكتشف نهر المسيسيبي.
I did that as a quick back page -- I had like four hours to do a back page
فعلت ذلك كغلاف خلفي سريع -- كان لي مثل أربع ساعات للقيام بـصفحة خلفية
for an issue of the Lampoon, and I did that,
لمسألة لامبون ، وفعلت ذلك ،
and I thought, "Well, I'm ashamed. I hope nobody knows it."
وفكرت : "حسنا ، أنا خجول. وآمل أن لا أحد يعرف ذلك ".
People wrote in for reprints of that thing.
كتب الناس يطلبون طبعات أخرى من هذا الشيء.
Urban absurdism -- that's what the New Yorker really calls for.
العبثية الحضرية,هذا ماتدعو اليه النويركر
I try to make life in New York look even weirder than it is with those covers.
وأنا أحاول أن تجعل الحياة في نيويورك تبدو أغرب مما هو عليه حتى مع تلك الأغلفة
I've done about 40 of them, and I'd say 30 of them are based on that concept.
لقد صممت نحو 40 منهم ، وأنا أقول أن نحو30 منهم على أساس هذا المفهوم.
I was driving down 7th Avenue one night at 3 a.m.,
كنت أقود في الجادة السابعة في ليلة ما في الثالثة صباحا
and this steam pouring out of the street, and I thought, "What causes that?" And that --
وهذا البخار يتصاعد من الشارع ، وكنت أفكر ، "ما هي أسباب ذلك؟" وذلك --
who’s to say?
من هذا؟
The Temple of Dendur at the Metropolitan in New York -- it's a very somber place.
معبد دندورفي متروبوليتان في نيويورك -- إنه مكان كئيب جدا.
I thought I could jazz it up a bit, have a little fun with it.
أعتقد أنه كان يمكن أن ألعب موسيقى الجاز قليلا ، وان أمرح فيه قليلا.
This is a very un-PC cover. Not in New York.
هذا هو غلاف ليس نتاج حاسب ألي. وليس في نيويورك.
I couldn't resist, and I got a nasty email from some environmental group saying,
لم أستطع المقاومة ، وجاتني رسالة بريد إلكتروني سيئة من جماعة ما مدافعة عن البيئة تقول :
"This is too serious and solemn to make fun of. You should be ashamed,
"وهذا أمر خطير جدا لا يجب ان تسخر منه. أنت يجب ان تشعر بالخجل ،
please apologize on our website."
الرجاء الاعتذار على موقعنا ".
Haven't got around to it yet but -- I may.
لم أصل اليه حتى الآن -- ولكن اسمحوا لي.
This is the word side of my brain.
هذا هو الجانب اللفظي من دماغي.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I love the word "Eurotrash."
أنا أحب كلمة Eurotrash.(القمامة الأوربية)
That's all the Eurotrash coming through JFK customs.
هذا كل الEurotrash القادمة من خلال جمارك مطار جون كنيدي.
This was the New York bike messenger meeting the Tour de France.
وكانت هذه دراجة نيويورك تجتمع بسباق فرنسا للدراجات.
If you live in New York, you know how the bike messengers move.
إذا كنت تعيش في نيويورك ، فإنك تعرف كيف تحرك درجات النقل .
Except that he's carrying a tube for blueprints and stuff -- they all do --
إلا أنه عليه حمل أنبوب للمخططات والاشياء -- يفعلون كل شيء --
and a lot of people thought that meant it was a terrorist
والكثير من الناس يعتقد ان ذلك يعني انه ارهابي
about to shoot rockets at the Tour de France --
على وشك اطلاق صواريخ في سباق فرنسا للدراجات --
sign of our times, I guess.
علامة على عصرنا ،أعتقد.
This is the only fashion cover I've ever done.
هذا هو غلاف المودة الوحيد الذي صممته
It's the little old lady that lives in a shoe, and then this thing --
انها السيدة المسنة الصغيرة التي تعيش في الأحذية ، ومن ثم هذا الشيء --
the title of that was, "There Goes the Neighborhood."
كان عنوان تلك ،"هنا تكون الجيرة"
I don't know a hell of a lot about fashion --
أنا لا أعرف الكثير عن الموضة --
I was told to do what they call a Mary Jane,
قيل لي أن تفعل ما يسمونه ماري جين ،
and then I got into this terrible fight between the art director and the editor saying:
وبعد ذلك وقعت في هذه المعركة الرهيبة بين المدير ورئيس التحريرالفني قائلا :
"Put a strap on it" -- "No, don't put a strap on it" -- "Put a strap on it -- "Don't put a strap on it" --
ضع رباط على ذلك ، لا ، لا تضع رباط عليه ، ووضع رباط على ذلك ، لا تضع رباط عليه ،
because it obscures the logo and looks terrible and it's bad and --
لأنه يحجب الشعار ويبدو رهيب وانه سيئ و--
I finally chickened out and did it for the sake of the authenticity of the shoe.
تخاذلت في النهاية وفعلتها من اجل سلامة الحذاء
This is a tiny joke -- E-ZR pass. One letter makes an idea.
هذة مزحة صغيرة -- البريد ZR بالمرور. حرف واحد يخلق فكرة.
This is a big joke.
هذه نكتة كبيرة.
This is the audition for "King Kong."
هذة هى بروفات "كينغ كونغ".
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
People always ask me, where do you get your ideas, how do your ideas come?
الناس يسألونني دائما ، من أين تحصل على أفكارك ، وكيف تأتي أفكارك؟
Truth about that one is I had a horrible red wine hangover,
الحقيقة حول تلك هو أننى كنت أعانى من وخم شرب النبيذ الاحمر
in the middle of the night, this came to me like a Xerox -- all I had to do was write it down.
في منتصف الليل ، جاءت لي مثل زيروكس -- جميع ما اضطررت الى القيام به هو الكتابة عنها.
It was perfectly clear. I didn't do any thinking about it.
وكان واضحا تماما. انني لم أقم بأي تفكير حياله.
And then when it ran, a lovely lady, an old lady named Mrs. Edgar Rosenberg --
وعندما ذهب بعد ذلك ، قامت سيدة جميلة ، وهي سيدة مسنة تدعى السيدة إدغارروزنبرغ -
if you know that name -- called me and said she loved the cover, it was so sweet.
إذا كنت تعرف بهذا الاسم -- قامت بالاتصال بي وقالت انها تحب الغلاف ، كان جميلا جدا
Her former name was Fay Wray, and so that was --
كان اسمها الأول فاي راي ، وهكذا كان
I didn't have the wit to say, "Take the painting."
لم يكن لدي من ذكاء لأقول "خذى اللوحة".
Finally, this was a three-page cover, never done before,
وأخيرا ، هذا هو غلاف من ثلاث صفحات ، لم يفعلها أحد من قبل
and I don't think it will ever be done again --
وأنا لا أعتقد أنه سيقوم أحد بذلك مرة أخرى -
successive pages in the front of the magazine.
صفحات متتالية في واجهة المجلة.
It's the ascent of man using an escalator, and it's in three parts.
انها ارتقاء رجل باستخدام المصعد ، وهى في ثلاثة أجزاء.
You can't see it all together, unfortunately, but if you look at it enough,
لا يمكنك مشاهدة كل ذلك معا ، للأسف ، ولكن اذا نظرتم اليها ما فيه الكفاية ،
you can sort of start to see how it actually starts to move.
يمكنك نوعا ما أن تبدأ رؤبة كيف تبدأ فعلا للتحرك.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Pretty elegant. Nothing like a crash to end a joke. That completes my oeuvre.
جميلة أنيقة.ما من شيء مثل حادث تحطم يصلح لانهاء نكتة. ها هو يكمل ما بدأته
I would just like to add a crass commercial --
أود فقط أن أضيف اعلانا تجاريا
I have a kids' book coming out in the fall called "Marvel Sandwiches,"
لدي كتاب للاطفال سيصدر في الخريف يسمى ب "السندويتشات الأعجوبة"
a compendium of all the serious play that ever was,
خلاصة وافية لجميع الألعاب الخطرة التي كانت
and it’s going to be available in fine bookstores, crummy bookstores,
وانها سوف تكون متاحة في المكتبات الفخمة، والمكتبات القذرة
tables on the street in October.
الطاولات في الشارع ، في اكتوبر تشرين الاول.
So thank you very much.
لذا شكرا جزيلا لكم.